Register of the William J. Niederpruem papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William J. Niederpruem papers
1914-1951
66024
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes and 6 oversize boxes (4 linear feet)
The William J. Niederpruem papers document the career of an American military officer who served in the United States Army during both World War I and World War II, and who was part of the American occupation authority in Japan after the end of the Second World War. As a staff officer with the 32nd Division, American Expeditionary Forces, Niederpruem served in France and Germany during 1918-1919. His collection includes orders and reports relating to this period, as well as a number of photographs and postcards depicting battlefield scenes from World War I. Much of the collection consists of printed matter, including pamphlets published by the American military during both world wars and serial issues with articles relating to World War II. There are also copies of newspapers with coverage of the ouster of General Douglas MacArthur during the Korean War.
Niederpruem, William J.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1966.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is arranged into 6 series: Military career file; Declassified U.S. government publications; Photographs; Postcards; Printed matter; and Oversize materials
Biographical note
1945-1946
1887 November 30 Born
1918-1919 Staff officer, American expeditionary forces
1930s-1940s Colonel, U.S. Army
1945-1946 Official with U.S. occupation authority in Japan
1972 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The William J. Niederpruem papers document the career of an American military officer who served in the United States Army during both World War I and World War II, and who was part of the American occupation authority in Japan after the end of the Second World War. As a staff officer with the 32nd Division, American Expeditionary Forces, Niederpruem served in France and Germany during 1918-1919. His collection includes orders and reports relating to this period, as well as a number of photographs and postcards depicting battlefield scenes from World War I. Much of the collection consists of printed matter, including pamphlets published by the American military during both world wars and serial issues with articles relating to World War II. There are also copies of newspapers with coverage of the ouster of General Douglas MacArthur during the Korean War.
The Military career file contains orders, reports, and intelligence summaries, as well as a translation done by Niederpruem of a study of World War I strategy by William Groener. The collection contains numerous maps pertaining to the Western Front during World War I and the Philippines during World War II. There are also a number of regional maps of Japan in the papers.
United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 32nd.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Military government.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--France.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- Military career file, 1918-1946
  - Article and clipping, 1919-1946 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Intelligence summaries prepared for the Army Air Forces, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Leaflets produced by Psychological Warfare Branch, U.S. Army Forces, Pacific Area, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Orders issued by General John J. Pershing, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Reports relating to the 32d Division, American Expeditionary Forces, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Telegram, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Translation by William J. Niederpruem of text by Wilhem Groener, "A Field Marshall against His Will - Strategical Studies Based Upon World War I", 1931 (Box-folder 1: 8-10)
- Declassified U.S. government publications, 1917-1918
  - American Expeditionary Forces, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Army War College, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 13-15)
- Photographs, 1918-1945
  - 8 prints depicting aerial views of World War I battlefields, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 1 print depicting American prisoners of war under German escort, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - 16 prints depicting American soldiers in France, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - 3 prints depicting French soldiers, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - 1 print depicting German soldiers in a trench, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - 8 prints depicting scenes of wartime devastation in France, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - 1 portfolio of 26 photographic reproductions depicting General Douglas MacArthur, American forces, and surrendering Japanese troops in the Philippines, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - 1 portfolio of 34 photographic reproductions depicting General Douglas MacArthur and scenes in Japan and Korea., 1945 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Postcards, 1916-1919
  - 24 cards depicting German and French soldiers, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - 5 cards depicting dead soldiers, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - 11 cards depicting wartime devastation in France and Germany, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - 7 cards depicting tanks, artillery pieces, and a barrage balloon, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - 1 card depicting a military hospital, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - 17 cards with illustrations depicting scenes of military and civilian life, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 14)
- Printed matter, 1916-1951
  - Brochures and pamphlets, 1916-1952
    - Japan, 1929-1952
      - 1929-1935 (Box-folder 2: 15)
      - 1936-1940 (Box-folder 2: 16)
      - 1952 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - World War I, 1916-1919
      - General, 1917-1919
        - 1917 (Box-folder 2: 18)
        - 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 19)
      - American Expeditionary Forces, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 20)
      - Army War College, 1917 (Box-folder 2: 21)
      - General Staff, British Army, 1916-1918
        - 1916 (Box-folder 2: 22)
        - 1917-1918 (Box-folder 2: 23)
    - World War II, 1942-1946
      - 1942 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
      - 1944-1945 (Box-folder 3: 3)
      - 1946 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Bulletins and newsletters, 1918-1949
    - Bulletin for Field Officers, 1918 December 1 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Current Affairs, 1942 April-August (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Daily Radio Digest, 1941 December 8-9 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Publications Analysis, 1948 August-September (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Spot News, 1941 December 8-9 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - TIPS, 1949 January 3 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - WAR, 1942 April-August (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Calendar published for the German military, 1937 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Clippings relating to the Munich Crisis and World War II, 1938-1941 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Monographs, 1917-1946
    - Anleitung für den Unteroffizier-Unterricht, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Hitler Doomed to Die, 1939 (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - Japan: Its People, Its History, Its Land, Its Work, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - Guide to Japan, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Grauer, Alvin, So I Went to Japan, 1946 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Tokyo Fall of 1945, 1946 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Nouët, Noël, Tokyo, 1946 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Programs, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Serial issues, 1930-1951
    - Army Information Digest, 1948 January (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Facts in Review, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Fortnight, 1951 April 2 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Newsweek, 1951 April 30 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - Time, 1939-1951
      - 1939 May 1-October 30 (Box-folder 4: 10)
      - 1951 April 23 (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - The Tourist, 1930 November (Box-folder 4: 12)
- Oversize materials, 1914-1951
  - Maps, 1914-1948
    - Miscellaneous, 1925-1945
      - Africa, 1940 (Box-folder 5: 1)
      - England (southern coast), 1934 (Box-folder 5: 2)
      - Europe and the Near East, 1940 (Box-folder 5: 3)
      - Germany, 1940 (Box-folder 5: 4)
      - Italy and the Balkan States, 1940 (Box-folder 5: 5)
      - Melbourne, Australia, 1934 (Box-folder 5: 6)
      - New Guinea, 1942 (Box-folder 5: 7)
      - North America, 1940 (Box-folder 5: 8)
      - Panama Canal, 1925 (Box-folder 5: 9)
      - Poland, 1937 (Box-folder 5: 10)
      - Western Front, 1939 (Box-folder 5: 11)
      - World atlas, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - Japan, 1945-1948
      - Central Japan, 1945 (Box-folder 6: 1)
      - Izu Peninsula, 1945 (Box-folder 6: 2)
      - Kanto District, 1945 (Box-folder 6: 2)
      - Tokyo, 1945-1948
        - 1945 (Box-folder 6: 4-5)
        - 1946 (Box-folder 6: 6-9)
        - 1947 (Box-folder 6: 10-11)
        - 1948 (Box-folder 6: 12-14)
    - Philippines, 1914-1945
      - General, 1914-1945
        - 1914 (Box-folder 7: 1)
        - 1945 (Box-folder 7: 2)
      - Infanta-Manila, 1945 (Box-folder 7: 3)
      - Manila, 1944-1945
        - 1944 (Box-folder 7: 4)
        - 1945 (Box-folder 7: 5)
      - Northern Philippines, 1938-1945
        - 1938 (Box-folder 7: 6)
        - 1945 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    - World War I, 1914-1919
      - March of the 32nd Division (American Expeditionary Forces) from the Meuse to the Rhine, 1919 (Box-folder 7: 8)
      - Bendorf, Germany, 1914 (Box-folder 7: 9)
      - France, 1918
        - Bar-le-Duc, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 10)
        - Beauvais, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 11)
        - Meaux, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 12)
        - Mulhouse, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 13)
        - Paris, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 14)
        - Soissons, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 15)
        - Verdun, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 16)
        - Wassy, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - Pamphlet with chart, Truth and Facts of the World War, 1928 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Proclamations issued by the German Army in occupied Belgium and France, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Serial issues, 1937-1950
    - Atlanta Georgian, 1939 September 2-5 (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - Atlanta Journal, 1939 September 3-1941 December 11 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - Army Navy Journal, 1943 December 7 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - Columbus Enquirer, 1939 September 2 -1941 December 12 (Box-folder 8: 6)
    - Daily Pacifican, 1945 September 5 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - Detroit News, 1941 December 8 (Box-folder 8: 8)
    - Deutsche Allgemeine Zeitung, 1938 June 18 (Box-folder 8: 9)
    - Free Philippines, 1945 April 13 (Box-folder 8: 10)
    - Germany, 1937 September (Box-folder 8: 11)
    - Holiday, 1950 February (Box-folder 8: 12)
    - Maptalk (supplements), 1945 July 25-August 8 (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - New York Times, 1941 December 8-9 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - Nippon Times, 1948 March 4 (Box-folder 9: 3)
    - Philadelphia Inquirer (supplement), 1942 April 23 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - PM, 1941 July 4-December 23 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - San Francisco Chronicle (supplement), 1941 December 14 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - Sunday American, 1939 September 3 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - Sunday Ledger-Enquirer, 1939 September 3-1940 April 28 (Box-folder 9: 8)
    - Times (London), 1939 September 6 (Box-folder 9: 9)
    - Völkischer Beobachter, 1938 October 1-5 (Box-folder 9: 10)
    - Yank, 1945 December 28 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Various newspapers with articles relating to General Douglas MacArthur, 1950-1951
    - San Francisco Call-Bulletin, 1951 April 11-19 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - San Francisco Chronicle, 1951 April 11-May 6 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - Stars and Stripes, 1950 January 26-27 (Box-folder 10: 3)